Guide to the Myron S. Falk Papers 1867-1950 MS 3047
New-York Historical Society
Myron S. Falk family papers
1867-1950
New-York Historical Society
Falk, Myron S. (Myron Samuel)
MS 3047
17.67 Linear feet in 17 boxes of various sizes and four oversize folders
The Myron S. Falk family papers include correspondence, financial ledgers, diaries, photographs, print matter, artifacts, and film pricipally related to Falk, a New York City based engineer, and his immediate family, and to a lesser extent to his wife Milly's family, the Einsteins. Myron Falk (1878-1945) worked as a consulting and chief engineer for the New York State Water Supply Commission and multiple construction and manufacturing companies. He was also on the Board of Directors or an officer of various institutions, including Wonham, Bates, and Goode Trading Corp. and Mt. Sinai Hospital. Additionally, Falk was Vice President at the American Bemberg Corporation, and served as a Lieutenant during World War I and World War II in the Ordnance Department building ammunition plants. For his work, Falk traveled often, going to Cuba, Brazil, and the Mediterranean, as well as China, Japan, and Korea with the American Silk Mission in 1923, during which he wrote detailed correspondence to his children.
Arrangement Note
The records are arranged in seven series as follows:
Series I. Travel (1888-1937)
Series II. Subject Files (1895-1945)
Series III. Financial and Legal Papers (1910-1947)
Series IV. Print Matter (1889-1932)
Series V. Photographs (1903-1928, undated)
Series VI. Artifacts (1869-1945, undated)
Series VII. Film (circa 1920s-1950s)
The collection arrived in a somewhat disorganized fashion and the processing archivist established the above overall organization. Nonetheless, if materials of various formats or subjects were found together in envelopes or folders, the archivist did not sort them into various series, but left them together. Therefore, although the series may appear rigid, the subject matter can be found in various parts of the collection. Accordingly, it is recommended that researchers look through all the series to ensure they have identified all relevant materials.
Biographical/Historical Note
Myron S. Falk was born in New York City on 13 September 1878. His parents were Arnold Falk (1843-1891) and Fannie Falk (1856-1920). Falk graduated as a Civil Engineer from Columbia University in 1899, and as a Mechanical Engineer from Stevens Institute in 1900. He received his Ph.D. from Columbia in 1904. He spent ten years at Columbia teaching in the Civil Engineering Department, where he wrote text books on the design of bridges with Professor of Civil Engineering, William A. Burr. While teaching, Falk was made head of the Testing Laboratory which resulted in his book "Cements, Mortars and Concretes." In 1904 he was appointed a member of the New York Bay Pollution Commission by Governor Benjamin B. Odell to investigate the pollution of New York Harbor. In 1905 he was appointed Consulting Engineer to the New York State Water Supply Commission, which had control and supervision of all water supplies in the state, including New York City. In 1905, he became Chief Engineer of the Godwin Construction Company. Two years later he became Chief Engineer of H.H. Oddie Inc, a New York construction firm. At the same time, he formed an association with Albert B. Hager, Civil Engineer, with whom he designed many steel building frames for architects.
In 1917 Falk was appointed Major in the Ordnance Department of the Army and was in charge of the production of raw materials for the Ammunition Division during World War I. He was promoted to Lieutenant Colonel before his retirement in July 1919. He became Chairman of the Board of Directors of Wonham, Bates & Goode Trading Corporation in 1920, which was a branch of M. Samuel & Co. Ltd, of London, an importing and exporting firm for whom he made trips to China, Japan, Brazil, Cuba, etc. In 1923, he traveled with the American Silk Mission to China, Japan, and Korea to discuss silk trade. He resigned his position at Wonham in 1927 to become Vice President and Chief Engineer of the American Bemberg Corporation, for which he built a large plant for the manufacture of rayon at Johnson City, Tennessee. He was also Consulting Engineer to many other projects, such as the construction of the Temple Emanu-El at 65th Street and Fifth Avenue in New York City. He also served as an officer and director of the Mercury Theatre.
Falk retired from all active work in 1928 but in 1941, in the months leading to America's entry into World War II, he returned to the Ordnance Department as Consulting Engineer to the Ammunition Division. Based primarily in Washington, Falk was a special assistant to the chief of the division on matters concerning the construction and operation of about seventy powder, explosives and loading plants. In late 1942, Falk was commissioned into the Army and assigned to the St. Louis Ammunition Branch as Head Engineer, before transferring in 1943 to the New York District as Principal Engineer of Industrial Production.
Falk was also associated with various organizations, some referencing his Jewish heritage, such as the Hebrew Technical Institute, the Institute for the Deaf, the Home for Aged and Infirm Hebrews, chairman of the Lavanburg Foundation, and trustee and chairman of the Building and Laboratory Committees of Mt. Sinai Hospital. He was in Harmonie Club, Engineers Club, Columbia University Club, and the Army-Navy Club.
In 1903, Falk married Milly Judith Einstein (1883-1915) whose father was Henry L. Einstein, a wool manufacturer and owner of New York Press. The Falks had two daughters, Eleanor and Mildred, and a son, Myron Falk Jr., who was known as "Johnny." Falk purchased in 1913 Tophill Farm on King Street in Greenwich, Conn.; the property is commonly referred to in the documents as being in Port Chester, N.Y., which was the closest town center/train station. After Falk's death in 1945, the property was sold to the Thermix Corporation as their new headquarters. It was in the vicinity of what is now the Brunswick School's pre-and lower schools.
[This biography was drawn primarily from biographical notes found within the collection, and a New York Times obituary.]
Access Restrictions
Materials are stored offsite and advance notice is required for use. Please contact manuscripts@nyhistory.org prior to your research visit to coordinate access. Keep in mind that it will take between two (2) and five (5) business days for collections to arrive, and you should plan your research accordingly.
Immediate Source of Acquisition Note
Gift of Robert Lewis Lenzner, 2016. Film donated by Nancy Falk and Michael S. Falk, 2016. Additional materials collected from various family members and donated by Nina Lenzner Evison, February 2021.
Scope and Contents Note
The Myron S. Falk papers include documents related to the personal and professional life of Myron S. Falk (1878-1945), an engineer from New York City. The collection spans from 1867-1947, although the bulk of the collection dates from the 20th century, after Falk graduated with a Civil Engineering degree from Columbia University (1899) and Mechanical Engineering degree from Stevens Institute of Technology (1900).
Falk's professional career is represented in this collection through his published works on engineering and his correspondence with companies he worked for, such as H.H. Oddie Inc, the American Bemberg Corporation, and the trading company Wonham, Bates, and Goode, for whom he would often travel.
A significant portion of travel correspondence, ephemera, and photographs derives from his journey in 1923 to China, Japan, and Korea with the American Silk Mission, which met with and discussed trade with silk manufacturers.
Additionally, there is an abundance of financial and legal documents regarding Falk and his family, including wills, estate and trust accounts, tax documents, ledgers, appraisals of his homes, and general financial correspondence and bills, some of which touch upon his involvement with Mercury Theatre.
There is also a scrapbook that contains information that commemorates important events involving Falk and his family, such as Columbia University Class of 1899 memorabilia, World War I and World War II clippings, clippings on their home Tophill Farm, and his children's wedding invitations and graduation pamphlets.
Also included in the collection is correspondence from Falk's time in the Ordnance Department during World War I and World War II, where he worked designing and manufacturing ammunition plants. Correspondence and artifacts also represent the numerous associations he was involved in, such as the Harmonie Club, the Society of American Magicians, Mt. Sinai Hospital committees, and Congregation Emanu-El. There is also a significant amount of condolence notes from when Falk died in 1945.
The collection also holds an assortment of photographs of his family and travels, some of which are in photo albums with captions or indexes, and others are loose with little identifying information.
Also in the collection are reels of film. Many of these were taken by Falk on his travels during the 1920s and later and many are home movies of his family. Several of the reels are from the years after Falk's death and were taken by Myron Falk, Jr. The family had many of these digitized and the digital files are on a USB and a set of DVDs.
Separated Materials Note
Nitrate negatives were removed from the collection and placed into separate storage.
Civil engineers -- New York (State) -- New York.; Decedents' estates -- New York (State); Jewish engineers -- New York (State) -- New York.; Blueprints (reprographic copies); Certificates.; Diaries.; Ephemera.; Financial records.; Home movies.; Letters (correspondence); Photographs.; Scrapbooks.; Asia -- Description and travel; Greenwich (Conn.); Einstein, Henry L., 1849-1918; Falk, Johnny, 1906-1992; Falk, Myron S. (Myron Samuel); Mercury Theatre; Mount Sinai Hospital (New York, N.Y.). Medical Board; Wonham, Bates & Goode Trading Corporation (New York, N.Y.)
- Series I. Travel, 1888-1937; 1.45 Linear feet
  Scope and Contents Note
  This series includes material related to Myron S. Falk's travels, much of which was done for the company Wonham, Bates & Goode for whom he was Chairman of the Board of Directors. Most documents are dated 1923 or after, excluding one travel diary written by Falk at 10 years old in 1888. There is also a diary that dates 1910-1934, in which Falk details some of the trips he went on, which also have material within this series. A set of snapshots from 1910-11 depict Myron and Milly on travels to Europe (primaily Italy) and to the Caribbean and Panama where they saw construction underway on the canal.
  A significant amount of material in this series was obtained in his journeys with the American Silk Mission, which was a group of businessmen who traveled around East Asia visiting silk manufacturers and factories in order to discuss the silk trade. Included are newspaper clippings from regional newspapers in Asia that welcomed the Silk Mission and give context to their travels, as well as itineraries and ephemera from each factory visited. There are also many photographs, some taken by Falk, which are more candid and also larger, posed ones given to him by the factories. Of particular significance is the detailed correspondence of his journeys through China, Japan, and Korea through which he not only details his daily travels, but also comments on cultural customs of these countries through a Western perspective. Korea was occupied by Japan during this period and the impact of that occupation is noted at times by Falk. Also within this correspondence is a description of a brief meeting with Sun Yat Sen, the first provisional President of the Republic of China.
  Arrangement Note
  This series is arranged in chronological order.
  - Travel diaries, 1888, 1910-1934 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 1)
    Includes two diaries. One is a travel diary written by Falk in 1888 concerning his travels in Germany, England, Austria, and France. The second diary, from 1910-1934, includes entries that relate to some of the material listed in this series. Includes some Jamaica-related documents from the diary.
  - Photographs (2 folders), 1910-1911 (Offsite-box 14)
    Scope and Contents
    Includes captioned snapshots from Myron and Milly's travels to Europe (1910) and Caribbean/Panama in 1911. Europe includes mostly various ports of call in Italy (Genoa, Naples, Sorrento, Amalfi, Pompei, Rome, Milan, Florence, Venice) as well as Azores, Madeira, and Algecira, with a few from England, Versailles, and on-board ships. Caribbean includes Puerto Rico/San Juan, Panama (canal construction), and Bermuda. (Part of 2021 gift)
  - General family correspondence, 1890-1943 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 2)
    Includes, among others, letters from Myron to his father (1890) and later letters between Myron and his children. Subject matter varies widely and includes some travel-related. Bulk sections of the correspondence date from the summer of 1928 and January-February 1936.
  - American Silk Mission. Correspondence to children (3 folders), 1923 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 3-5)
    Includes three typed transcripts of Falk's correspondence to his children during his trip with the American Silk Mission to China, Japan and Korea during 1923. Includes, among other things, a description of a meeting with Dr. Sun Yat Sen, first provisional president of Republic of China and leader of the Chinese Nationalist Party.
  - American Silk Mission. Documents and ephemera (4 folders), 1923 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 6-9)
    Includes menus, itineraries, invitations, informational brochures, newspaper clippings, correspondence, and photographs obtained throughout China, Japan, and Korea.
  - American Silk Mission. Photographs (1 of 3), 1923 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 10)
  - American Silk Mission. Photographs, oversize (2 of 3), 1923 (Drawer Oversize Large)
    Panorama of participants in the American Silk Mission in China.
  - American Silk Mission. Photographs, flat file (3 of 3), 1923 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 3)
    Photographs from dinners during American Silk Mission. Includes Yokohama Raw and Waste Silk Guild, Chamber of Commerce and Silk Guild of Nanzing, China Export Co. Lmt. (Shanghai), Yung Tah Silk Filature & Soy Lun Anchor Filature (Shanghai).
  - American Silk Mission. Newspapers, 1923 (Box Oversize Small, Folder 1)
    Includes articles welcoming the American Silk Mission from Nanshin Hibi Shinbun and The Japan Advertiser.
  - American Silk Mission. Rolled textile, flat file., 1923 (Offsite-box 7)
  - Mediterranean. Correspondence to children during trip, 1927 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 11)
  - Brazil. Correspondence to children during trip, 1930 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 12)
    Includes a copy of daughter Mildred's birth certificate, Myron's small pox vaccination record, and photographs.
  - Correspondence, 1930-1934 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 12A)
    4 letters: from New York (1930), on board Vulcania (1931), on board Virginia (1932), and at Panama Canal Zone (1932). Photocopy of 1932 passenger list of Scythia and obituary of Falk mentor William Hubert Burr (1934).
  - Caribbean and Central America. Photographs (2 folders), 1934 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 13-14)
    Unbound photo album of travels to Cuba, Jamaica, Panama, Costa Rica, and Miami. Contains an original typed index with descriptions of each photo. The archivist wrote numbers on the backing of each photograph in brackets to facilitate the use of the index with the corresponding photo.
  - Mediterranean. Correspondence from Myron and Mildred to family, 1937 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 15)
- Series II. Subject Files, 1895-1945; 2.40 Linear feet
  This series includes Myron Falk's correspondence and related documents, spanning from 1895 to 1945, on a wide variety of subjects of a personal and professional nature. Included are subjects relating to his work as an engineer and other associations he took part in, such as the State Water Supply Commission, the American Bemberg Plant, Congregation Emanu-El, his work in the Ordnance Department during World War II, the Harmonie Club, and Mount Sinai Hospital. Also included are his school notebooks, documents relating to his house in Greenwich, Conn., his personal diaries and address books, and clippings concerning Orson Welles's Mercury Theatre. The scrapbook folders also contain material related to his family, such as his son Myron Falk Jr.'s graduation from Yale and his daughter's wedding invitations. There is also mixed general correspondence that contains documents often related to Falk's club memberships, Columbia, engineering jobs, and the American Silk Mission.
  This series is arranged by subject matter.
  - Diaries (2 folders), 1908-1938 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 16-17)
  - WWII/Ordnance Dept. documents (4 of 6 folders), 1942-1944 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 18-21)
    Includes ammunition plant organizational maps, correspondence, and Falk's handwritten notes.
  - WWII/Ordnance Dept. documents (1 of 6 folders), 1940-1942 (Offsite-box 14, Folder 3)
    Notebook with Falk's notes and other documents concerning various US ordnnce production facilities. (Part of 2021 gift.)
  - WWII/Ordnance Dept. documents (1 of 6 folders). Oversize, 1942-1944 (Box Oversize Small, Folder 1)
    Includes oversized Ordnance organizational charts and maps.
  - Water Supply Commission (3 folders), 1905-1906 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 22-24)
    Includes documents and correspondence relating to the State Water Supply Commission report, including a report by Falk as the Consulting Engineer of the commission.
  - Bemberg Plant clipping and photographs, 1927 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 1)
    From the The Bristol Herald Courier. Includes preservation photocopies and original clipping.
  - Congregation Emanu-El documents, 1927-1929 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 2)
    Includes plans and descriptions of the new building at 65th and Fifth Avenue.
  - Mount Sinai Hospital correspondence, 1938-1940 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 3)
    Includes correspondence and reports (e.g., statistical and comparative) from Mount Sinai Hospital to committee members, especially related to the Medical Board's Dental Committee (e.g., organizational structure, services to German refugees, appointments).
  - Home for Aged and Infirm Hebrews, 1937-1938 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 4)
    Includes correspondence and minutes from the meeting of the Executive Committee of the Home, which Falk was invited to as Chairman of the Building Committee. Includes the "Preliminary Study for the Future Development of the Home for Aged and Infirm Hebrews" (1937) and correspondence from architects Robert D. Kohn and Charles Butler.
  - Greenwich property septic tank correspondence, 1942 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 5)
  - Oversized property maps and blueprints, 1913-1930 (Drawer Oversize Large)
    Includes Greenwich topographical map, septic tank blueprint, linen prints of the house (1913), and a map of Greenwich (1930). Also includes a supplementary drawing of W. 53rd Street showing Route No. 101 for the subway system (1928).
  - School notebooks (3 folders), 1895-1902 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 6-8)
    Includes notebooks from a course in Practical Metallurgy at Columbia University, and from his travels visiting factories in Pennsylvania.
  - Address book, Undated (Offsite-box 2, Folder 9)
  - The Tennyson Birthday Book, Undated (Offsite-box 2, Folder 10)
  - Engagements/Appointments Book, circa 1903? (Offsite-box 14, Folder 4)
    Social engagements for a period November-May of an unspecified year. Appears to be Milly Falk's book. (Part of 2021 gift.)
  - Myron & Milly Wedding (2 folders), 1903 (Offsite-box 14, Folder 5-6)
    Includes a "souvenir" "Bride's Book" that includes some entries about the couple and their wedding. Also includes a "record of gifts" and many congratulatory telegrams and letters that had been placed inside the front cover of the Bride's Book. (Part of 2021 gift)
  - Scrapbook (1 of 7 folders), 1922-1934 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 11)
    These papers were found loose in the cover of the scrapbook. They include, among other material and subjects, an assortment of bills, correspondence, the 1934 catalog for the Hebrew Technical Institute, documents regarding a dispute about renovations to the Century Country Club, and material related to the American Silk Mission (articles from the Yokohama Tsushin, passenger list of the ship Empress of Australia, etc.).
  - Scrapbook (2 of 7 folders), 1906-1939 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 12)
    The unbound scrapbook includes, among other material, newspaper clippings of family achievements, including real estate transactions; clippings and publicity pieces about the Mercury Theater and its productions; travel ephemera; programs from Temple Emanu-El and Columbia University reunions; and correspondence from the Ordnance department (World War I) and from Wonham, Bates & Goode.
  - Scrapbook (3 of 7 folders), 1910-1943 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 13)
    Includes, among other material, clippings about Henry L. Einstein and other family members (obituaries, announcements, etc.), and bills from European travel (1910).
  - Scrapbook (4 of 7 folders), 1899-1925 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 14)
    Includes, among other material, clippings from groups and companies Falk was associated with, such as the American Bemberg Company, State Water Supply Commission, Mount Sinai Hospital, and Columbia University.
  - Scrapbook (5 of 7 folders), 1899-1944 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 15)
    Includes material from Columbia University, Mt. Sinai, and the Harmonie Club. Includes a list of all members of the American Silk Mission, with titles and associated companies.
  - Scrapbook (6 of 7 folders), 1930-1945 (Offsite-box 2, Box 16)
    Includes, among other material, a handwritten biography of Myron S. Falk.
  - Scrapbook (7 of 7 folders), 1922-1932 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 17)
    Includes, among other material, three letters from Myron Falk's father postmarked from Amsterdam (1890) that are written in another language (possibly Dutch), his WWI military record, and correspondence.
  - Condolences on the death of Myron S. Falk (4 folders), 1945 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 18-21)
    Includes related correspondence.
  - Yale Graduation (2 folders), 1928 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 1-2)
    Includes materials from Myron S. Falk, Jr.'s graduation from Yale in 1928. See also Photographs Series for an oversize panorama of the graduating class.
  - Chinese porcelains guide, 1921-1931 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 3)
    Includes a copy of "Chinese Porcelains, Their History and How to Distinguish Their Dates and Styles" by Major Arthur De Bles from the Art Culture Institute of America. Also includes some travel ephemera and some correspondence.
  - General correspondence (2 folders), 1920-1923 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 4-5)
    Includes Wonham, Bates & Goode Trading Corporation correspondence, bills, Falk's driver's license, estimates for Mt. Sinai Hospital, some American Silk Mission documents, and other matters.
- Series III. Financial and Legal Papers, 1905-1947; 1.96 Linear feet